[Music]
so
that was just blues entry music
hello and welcome everyone to actin flab
live stream number zero 36.1
it's january 19th
welcome to the actin flap
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at the links here on
this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
you can check out activeinference.org to
learn about how to participate in any
active lab events which go beyond but
also support the live streams
and also the coda site at the bottom
will give you access to the table with
metadata on the past and upcoming live
streams
all right
today in
acting stream number 36.1 we're going to
be
discussing and learning and seeing who
joins
for the paper modeling ourselves what
the free energy principle reveals about
our implicit notions of representation
by sims and pazulo 2021
we went over some of the background in
36.0
and today we're just going to
introduce ourselves say hello what we
were excited about in the paper and then
we wrote down some things to discuss
but i'm sure both of you have other
random things you wrote down and
anything that people write in a live
chat we can also
look at so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and
i think i'm excited to just hear
dean's marginal
comments
and just see where it goes because this
there's just a lot in this paper and so
it's just a
it'll be a thick dot one
well i'm i'm dean i'm here in calgary
and uh
i
really didn't know if i even had time to
even look at this paper and then
i
i listened in on
daniel and blue's conversation in the
zero and that it
piqued my interest and so
uh i read the paper and i got really
really
i was really happy to read this paper
because um where you were daniel and
blue
kind of took a a path to introducing the
material
uh this is this is kind of familiar
ground familiar territory for me which
is very unusual because most of
the stuff that we look at i'm looking at
it for the first time and so
i'm really excited and i don't want to
detour anything that you guys want to
sort of look at at the point one
maybe at the point two point of this
process we can look at what the section
five of this paper what can we learn
from this debate because i think that
section five of this is
super
interesting and not just trippy you guys
use the word trippy which i thought was
fantastic quite uh
quite a good description but i i think
we can pull
parts of this um
out and look at them and reassert them
and reattach them in our own way and
actually come up with something pretty
uh
pretty amazing
i'll pass it down to blue
hi everyone i'm blue i'm a researcher in
new mexico
and this paper um
it was great like like dean was saying
um
it was familiar to me but not because of
my background just i i thought it really
um
explained and summarized a lot of like
different points in the fep and active
inference and how we use it to model
ourselves and
it it pulled out a lot of really
important questions i think that i'm
looking to
looking forward to discussing with you
guys
so we wrote down some things to discuss
but maybe
let's start with just a blank slate
dean what do you think would be some
approaches that we can take or some
starting points
because we already have
other cards up our sleeve
well i don't want to be i don't want to
be a
guy holding up a flag and detouring your
conversation one of the things we might
get to near closer to the end hopefully
is
the authors speak to the possibility of
you know when you set up your table
daniel you one of the things that they
potentially talked about in the section
five of the paper is
the idea that the um lines are a little
bit fuzzy here maybe they're broken
and the idea of in some cases our
ability to move from the
non-representational
into the representational
it's kind of a big deal because you can
have the debate that says here's the
parts that would align with a
non-representational view and here's the
lines that would parts that would align
with a representational view but then
they insert this part that says but
maybe
we slip into and out of these
representations kind of like we slip
into and out of the q density and so
maybe at near closer to the end today
we can tap into that a bit
let's start with that
grid
yeah
because this is the structure of the
paper and
the
uh elucidating contribution
and also i think dave left a youtube
comment or something like there's other
dimensions so this is kind of
pointing away towards an interesting
approach to
uh making sense of some philosophical
debates kind of laying them out in
tables like this
so
how should we approach it there's the
representational and the
non-representational
perspectives or stances or modes or
archetypes that is definitely very
blurry because of course it depends on
what you mean by representation
and that can have some fundamental
ambiguity
and then that representational
versus not continuum or
dialectic
is then
separated into a few
domains
i think
we could talk about what are the
similarities and differences because
some of it was a little
nuanced and i wondered if there was
other categories or
they were organizational structural
content related and functional so then
this is your game board of eight
lower dimensional projections
that the thought can be in
or it's something like one of these
eight
uh octants
and then a lot of the papers going
through some of the literature
and
rhetoric for and against
each of
these using the fep as kind of the
interpretand
what is being interpreted to speak for
one of those eight cells
what do either of you
want to
continue it there
well on the action domains on that
sensory motor stuff and
yellie bloomberg talks a good a good
a good argument around the idea that
for example i could be in a flow state
and there is no model that i'm or plan
that i'm necessarily following and
that's true if we're talking about
extension and
and and embedded as two of those four
e's
um you don't necessarily have to move to
that place that requires
something to
work off of you could just be flowing
and working in something right
that that
that
rate of change
is is you extended
so
there are there are times when
you literally don't have to be working
off of a plan you could also be moving
from a blueprint
to some kind of outcome that you want to
achieve
and then
that
it's pretty obvious then that the
representational piece has to exist
um so
maybe the argument isn't that both
aren't
at work it's how
we transition
from a density
out of a density and then back into a
density
something something to
at least have a conversation about
because i think blue was touching on
this last time too she said
i just want somebody to be able to show
me how
how these lines are in this this sort of
structured relationship exist because
and i when i when i heard to say that i
was kind of like
no i think that's a that's a fair
question because those those lines seem
to be blurred
so something that came up yesterday um
is the idea of free will
and um i just wonder how that might play
into
these different
grid boxes like like is there
free will
in all of these or in none of them or
is that even related
okay
let's write it down
one interesting thing about this
is it has a little bit of that visual
illusion
with the black
grid and the white dots at the junctions
so it's kind of a
perceptive artifact
it's just sort of messing with our
visual representation and visual
representations are
are you know when you see it you believe
it that kind of
focused system in a lot of the active
literature and vision
uh okay
so let's let's
save free will and the the blurriness
for later and then come to some of the
things we wrote down for the previous
list
okay
so in what sense can or are
computational models or any other kind
of models be fully observable
can i can i give maybe a possible
[Music]
real-life example that maybe speaks
starts to speak to that sure
okay so
in the paper he um the authors say
however these differences matter if one
considers structural aspects and the
degree of resemblance between hidden
variables
and environmental dynamics
so i was thinking about your question
and i so i wrote this down if dynamics
then the material i.e the content the
structure and the organization is going
to have a different change rate
than the function so the first the first
three columns are going to
behave
differently than the fourth
for example the screwdriver
as tool remains very stable hopefully
relative to the spiral effect or
function than it can generate on the
screw
to the one driving the screw there are
now two rates to juggle
the assumption that the tool applying
the function as a rule is stable and
consistent and the effect sought
will be a form change meaning action
orientation
or a new representation outcome
happens
you quite literally start and end with a
dance
between the stabilities and the dynamics
leveraging off of each other
so back and forth so we need to keep
open the possibility that the the stable
or the representational
and the dynamic which
as yelly points out can be
non-representational as well
are both in play
and then i wrote here because i've used
the expression when in doubt zoom in
zoom out when mark off blanket
zoom in zoom out
so in terms of in terms of the
computation there's actually two
computations one around around what we
think should remain relatively
consistent
and one which we
then apply that consistency
to something that we actually want to
see a rate change
expedited
so there's actually i think there's two
calculations here
to the person that's trying to figure
out
how they're going to
see what's on the other side of the
blanket
very
interesting lorenzen laplace
so i like this idea of um zooming in and
out with a markov blanket um and i think
it speaks to
the the way that um
agents are nested or
or anything is nested i don't want to
necessarily ascribe agency or free will
um to
different levels of organization but um
i think when markup blanket zoom in
different marker blankets zoom out
different markov like it so for me like
it speaks to
multi-scale systems
and how applying markup blankets is kind
of
scale-friendly or like imputed onto the
the system in question
one
extension or maybe example of that
we've probably talked before like the
table it's
in the process ontology it's material
that's tabling but then that material is
also process based so sort of this
multi-scale process ontology and the
identification of a given system of
interest at stationarity like an object
that can be tracked
with but there's objects that are too
fast to be tracked and there's objects
that are too slow to be tracked below
the just noticeable difference and so
within a given measurement or um
active inference regime
a given entity can
have a
attention on a given system of interest
it can't have attention on things that
are slower or faster like out of its
frequency band
but
that's discarding 99 of the system
to
not consider outside of the frequency
band
it's like the observables are just
one
they're they're very bounded
and so that
the slower things are the larger things
and the faster things are the smaller
things
so that's kind of a nice
and and and let me just piggyback on
that
and if we're talking about specificity
or
scale friendly
versus
um cosmic and scale free that's also
part of that zoom in zoom out
exercise because there there are quite
literally elements of this that are
still scale free
that if again
as they said modeling ourselves we can
we can
we can start from that position of scale
free and then find the specifics or we
can find the specifics
and ask ourselves how far
out can we extend our
confidence that the stability will hold
so that's again
piggyback on what you just said daniel
there's all there's all kinds of ways of
interpreting
zoom in and zoom out and i think that's
maybe that's one of the insights
that we get when we don't get ourselves
hung up on being a really radical
an activist
even though i i'm of the camp that says
we start out in the non-representational
and activist
leaning side and then we
the plans and the representations and
the
effects of that are representational
all right i'll think of an example that
uh
a wet lab example so i'm thinking of
doing
pcr or a wet lab technique where you're
not observing perhaps the outcomes of
what's happening for multiple steps and
even then it might be a color change or
a number on a screen
and so then you get limited observables
those are sometimes your degrees of
manipulation like in a thermocycler
that's changing the temperature the only
thing you're measuring during the
reaction is the temperature sometimes
you might also look at like the optical
property but usually just changing the
temperature
and then it's very representation like
to have a mental or a cognitive
representation which can include
extended
phenotype like the notebook and the
computer but that's pretty
representational to have counterfactuals
about what molecules would do that have
never been visually observed
and so
science becomes
representational
and i think
how
far does that reach back and it kind of
blurs off into increasingly
non-representational forms
not saying that science is the most
representational thing but
what are the most representational
things
and how do we move back and forth on
that is what i'm seeing with the
two feet in two feet out
but you just hit on a really important
point because you said science becomes
so so what makes up the becomes
like what what exists in that
that space
prior to it
us all agreeing that it's now science
and i think that's
what this
i think that's what this modeling as
opposed to
us as model
asks us to consider
that's a really that's a really you you
touched on the the big the big deal here
abductively
so what makes up that what what what has
to be present for us to be able to say
okay now you've crossed a threshold and
now we're talking science
yep
it reminds me of the paper of
burnberg anticipating brain is not a
scientist
and we can just take uh
the always prescient titles and content
of these papers to be targeting
attention point like is the markov
blanket a valid or useful construct more
recently but back several years ago
identifying
some similarities
or at least a uh
area of interaction
with
the anticipatory
and cybernetics of systems which is
pretty
system agnostic can apply to
very abstract
representations as well as perhaps real
systems
and then the physical brain hypotheses
and the
inactivist and ecological perspectives
on cognition
with
this activity
called science and the role of a
scientist
and so
a few ways to parse science
um one is uh as we heard from majeed
benny recently with model-based science
so that's one like relevant way that we
learned about and talked about this
recently like science being the
application of models
but then
other systems are perhaps doing
something different well what is science
anyone in the live chat should
definitely respond what is science and
also i would like to hear what both of
you think and how that relates to
anything we're talking about here or
ever so so i always think about science
as the application of the scientific
method to anything right like so
observations hypothesis experiment et
cetera um
and
because i think of science like like
this
science itself
is
just a model also right like so so we
use science like we build a model of
whatever phenomenon it is that we're
trying to replicate or
observe or test or whatever
um and we do we experiment with our
model like essentially so so
the scientific method itself is a model
for doing science and then the process
of
doing it
is creating a model of of the world so
it's like nested models all the way down
in science in my world
so blue can i ask you a quick question
do you what do you think
precedes
[Music]
the
engagement with what you're describing
is or is or
because the authors always say
assumptions matter
what what assumptions do you think goes
into a person saying okay well now i'm
going to use scientific method
are there are there things that that
priors that we should
sort of pull out and examine
that are consistent when a person gets
to a place where they say okay well i'm
gonna i'm gonna do that
yeah i mean so so there's a lot of um
stuff that's in the scientific when i
say the scientific method it's like i
mean it encompasses things like
scientific bias and uh positive control
and a negative control and and so all of
these things are kind of this in this
like umbrella
category when i say scientific method um
an experimental design like is is not
always simple but but definitely like
what
precedes any science happening is simply
observation right like so you have to
like be observant and and to have
observation you have to
have some instrument with which to
measure or gauge the phenomena which
you're
trying to
examine right so even if it's just your
brain
um
like which is probably the most powerful
instrument of all of the instruments
because it's fundamental to any test in
a testable
instrument that tests anything in the
world so i think um yeah like that so
that's a lot of priors i think
so so
is it fair to say then
that to get to a place of
of adopting a scientific method
one might
first possess before they can actually
get into the formalities of that
a field seeking curiosity and a way
finding bias
and those are two different things right
one is i can be a spectator the other
one is i've got to get in the boat i've
got to get my skin in the game do you
think that those two things are
necessary
to adopt
scientific method or to commit to
scientific method
so
i'd like for you to unpack those a
little bit more so um
yeah can you just describe what you mean
about like the those two the wayfinding
and the the curiosity and yeah yeah the
field seeking curio well curiosity i
mean it's got it's kind of got four
parts right there's there's an epistemic
piece
there's a
sensing piece
um i can't remember what the other two
are right off the top of my head but but
bottom line is that curiosity doesn't
just it's not sort of a monolith
um and and part of
that
determination because you don't know but
you you still
you're you're you're prepared to put in
some time and effort
uh
to get past not knowing means that you
can take one of two essential paths you
can find out
right you can go to a source that
already knows or you can figure out
um based on sort of collecting and
curating
um evidence
so that that's the that's the field
seeking piece and then the thing wait
wait wait what's the difference between
finding out and figuring out like to me
those are the same so like whether
you're collecting evidence like from
google or from
that's epistemic right but to to figure
out is to
is to
not have a source already
not a single source of truth
that would be the difference so one you
can find you can find a truth source and
then either believe it or not and the
other is you have to you have to develop
your own
truth
through
it takes a lot more time because you
have to go around and gather a whole
bunch of other
bits of information that aren't
necessarily pre-packaged for you does
that make sense
yeah and and also like what is truth
well right right i mean you ultimately
have to be the one that decides that
right whether to trust and have
confidence in something or not
cool lots of um
yeah
go for it no go ahead daniel
um so let's pull one level back from or
two from one and a half fractional
dimensions from the curiosity fourfold
distinction
there was like the personal factors so
the question was what precedes the type
of engagement that might be called
scientific
right and there's some personal factors
they're basically psychodynamic or like
situational
behavioral
archetypes but they're things about
individual uh
people humans what other kind of factors
even if the individual is the nexus of
agency what other factors come into play
and like what precedes the kind of
engagement that might be called
scientific if the person is our system
of interest what do we how do we zoom in
and out from there
well that that's my that's my question
my question isn't i don't have an answer
necessarily but what i have is
so you know before the big bang kind of
thinking we don't know
but is it possible that there actually
is something that we can put our finger
on
that leads someone to
have confidence in a scientific method
and not just sort of
remain in a kind of in a
place of stasis
and and not be curious right because
there's lots and lots of people who are
kind of
quite comfortable just going going along
with whatever
is happening around them but then
there's others that appear to have
um
a potential for a deeper commitment so
when
so for example when
when we were talking prior to mcgee
coming with us
on with us um
blue
raised the specter that
genes don't necessarily
have to have time
in order to be
considered prediction matter expertise
because it has both the cause and the
effect
included in the
in the structure
so that got me curious right like
some for some people just making that
statement or that or asking that
question
blow right by them they wouldn't even
give it a second thought but then for
some people
just making that claim arrests them
slows them down
and gets them asking questions on their
own now so that's why i'm asking this in
the context of so why would somebody
now
go from i don't care i don't give a
rat's backside about science too i i'm
very passionate about science i'm very
interested in learning this method
so i think um science really is seen by
many as a kind of truth-finding
endeavor
uh um
because whether it's through
mining previous knowledge or generating
new information
maybe knowledge um
either one of those is definitely like
like a
a
thinking of the truth
um
and in that way like
aren't we all just looking to like
minimize our uncertainty reduce our
uncertainty
so so i look at science like like it is
an uncertainty reduction
task i mean that's the the point of it
perhaps
so i don't know what factors um
you know other than the fact that like
maybe we're in a simulation
like we could go there
um because that that would like precede
the scientific endeavors that we
undertake in our truth-finding
efforts
um
but but really like the knowledge of
science as a way to determine truth um i
think
might be
part of it i mean and maybe not everyone
is taught that
um i think about like you know in
western culture we're all like
indoctrinated with the scientific method
from i don't know fourth grade on or
something like that right
and then they give you the phd at the
end when you're fully indoctrinated but
but here's the thing blue and this is a
but you bring up a really cool point in
you know fourth grade indoctrinated and
i think one of the things you and i have
kind of gone we volleyed back and forth
is so
yes science and so somebody has has said
this is a this has got some practical
things and some truth finding things but
i've always come back with
great
science
plan these these are material things my
question has always been when and you
bring up the
well we've decided when it's grade four
but
i'm not sure that some someone who's
pray for let me see that be about
nine ten years of age is saying it's the
same sciences for somebody who's 29 30
or 39 40 right
so
what i'm suggesting is is that before
the the the plan or the science
there's something before that some
really important things that we're just
assuming or
willfully
ignoring
because
now we're onto the plan right because
that's what has been reified and and
given the the
the holy blessing
sort of thing so so i think you're
you're hitting something that that's
critical and it's why i'm disagreeing
with you so i don't think that the
science that you're doing when you're
nine is that different from the science
that you're doing when you're 39 um
and
the perfect example of that is um
a feinman like i was reading i don't
remember maybe it's in in the meaning of
it all like maybe it's in that book but
um you know he talks about
how like for him he just plays right and
so for a lot of his science is like oh i
get to like
make this toy and play with it and try
to look at it and i keep playing with it
and i keep playing with it and so
you this is something i think that's
like innate in us like to just the
figuring out part like the truth-finding
part so even as a baby like from the
time you can sit up like what is this
block like what is the shape what is the
slinky right like it's finding out and
figuring out
like what are the affordances of the
objects right right and um
some of them are imposed by the outside
like don't stand on the chair
um because kids will use chairs as tents
and step stools and you know like so
it's
some of it like that we impose some
structure on you can't use this toy in
that way
but but really like kids will don't they
don't know they'll use anything anyway
like they'll they do all kinds of crazy
things like like they'll you know
slide down a mountain on you know
a trash bag or something right like so
they don't know right how to
what what the limits are
um
and so they'll explore new limits and i
think that scientists um at least the
ones that really love to do science
uh play a lot
also so so again the
the the trial and error piece
can be like the triangles piece it can
be scale free and i would never push
back
on that
piece the epistemic and the specific is
what you just described the other two
parts of curiosity are the distributed
and the sensing and that's kind of the
sort of the more
active
part
where you have to kind of go out and do
the skin in the game you have to get in
get in the boat across the south pacific
you can be doing the epistemic and the
specific as well because you can be
taking samples but
you can get you can kind of see that
there's another
side to this so my my question around
the wind isn't around the
the um
[Music]
the ability to see the scale free part
of it my question is is if i'm a 10 year
old
and there's something before the plan
how sophisticated is that something
relative to the something before the
plan as a 40 year old
i i just don't think that the
experiences that a 10 year old has
and the resources that they necessarily
draw upon are the same so i do think
there's also a specific and a scale
friendly
part to this
would you
would you push back on that
i mean i think that we all kind of just
operate on whatever level that like i i
do agree like that the knowledge of a 10
year old isn't the same as the knowledge
of of a 40 year old but um i i think you
know
we just operate at whatever level that
we're at similarly like a baby you know
like they're just doing their own kind
of truth finding but so the process is
the same like even though the priors may
differ
i think the process is similar
this reminds me of in the linguistics
guest stream with elliot murphy how
there's the view of language as the
construct
like subject verb object and then
there's the language as learned by each
learner and so i'm almost hearing like
blue saying it's the same process
everyone's on the same trip but of
course recognizes that each learner is
going to have individuated factors
including like what they specifically
know maybe has some correlations or
um whatever with age or with other
features
and then that's
i feel like maybe partially reflected
with a specific
of the
um
like
if yeah is the nine-year-old and the
four-year-old learning the same science
it's either it's like pan scientism or
uni uh solipsism scientism everybody's
in their own scientific niche and so
it's just a million different granules
and then the other hand the other end of
that extreme debate would be it's all
one integrated extended cognitive
process which i wrote some notes on so
dean go for that and then we'll think
about it as more of an extended
continuous process
yeah and again i'm not i'm not trying to
i don't want to sort of shoehorn
something in here and then
so i would always i would always hear
from people in my
history
um the expression um
well i know that's a problem there i
guess you're just gonna have to get
creative you're gonna have to think
outside the box and being the um
insurgent and the
non-compliant person that i am i would
say i would come back with and i was
reporting to people i would come back
with so tell me about this box
what makes up the box what makes up the
process
and of course that didn't make me very
popular because nobody could get
specific about what
what's inside or what makes up
that three-dimensional space
and and i i think it's the same thing
with we can say well there's a process
well tell me
then
why a 10 year old thinks
in the same way as a 40 year old does
what evidence what what what what are
you hooking
that
assumption on
and again i'm not i'm not trying to be a
pill here i want i'm really curious what
would make a 10 year old think
the same way as somebody with an
additional 30 years
of experience
they want uncertainty reduction
that's a generalization that i can agree
with but what about the specifics i'll
give a specific in a general i think
that for disciplinary education some of
the questions might be very similar like
why is this leaving group superior to
that one
in organic chemistry i think if somebody
were very precocious and 10 and learning
about the halides as leaving groups or
if they were learning about it in adult
education they would ask that question
and then once they
got the answer they would have moved on
in their learning in that disciplinary
finding out way like here's the periodic
table here's why the trend is this way
so
that's not the whole of education but in
that
mode
which many of us have come from and
exist within
that was the education that's
educational instruction
so that's the instructionism component
and then i think it becomes different as
you move away from that spotlight
um so then a few other comments like
about the specifics of how the different
age would be different
um
there's
the the biology of how the individuals
would be different
like in uh
some of their cognitive features
whatever it meant for that person from
working memory to the specific long-term
memories and other capabilities they
have
perspectives they've learned about
um
[Music]
they're a different complex system
but
they can be a complimentary part of a
system
like older people providing mentorship
for younger people but i think that's
what kind of um comes to some of these
notes on science as an extended
cognitive phenomena which is partly what
has been got at
um
so science has many different
possible
goals and sometimes scientists in an ad
hoc way will appeal to different
components like science is correct
because there's technology like it's
demonstrable or it's useful
um not always providing a null
hypothesis for what we would have
if we had done something different but
there's all kinds of different
uh
ways to look at it but
it deals with individual cognitive
features
and learning an action in their niche
but it also refers to broader
phenomena like maybe a differentiating
question is can one person
on an island by themselves do science
and if the answer is like yes they could
explore and hypothesis test then that's
one
perspective another perspective would be
you're only doing science when you're
using
this interpretation of the scientific
method and
you're using science as a body of
knowledge like you're using the
literature with the dois
and some people go as far to say that
you need to have a career in a certain
specific institution or a specific
degree or a specific training
or approach
so
that is clearly not applicable to the
one person on the island and not that
one of them is better but that whole
apparatus that's part of the extended
niche
and then also there's at least in our
case
the emphasis on the digital or at least
informational stigma g
like there's a recognition in science in
a different way than like there's many
books you could read on um
tying knots probably a lot of youtube
channels
um
[Music]
is there a doi for information on knots
probably not but
that um in science is a big emphasis
reading and writing the literature
at least in the way that we know it
today but again that could also
perhaps not be as much of a core
component anyways just like a few
points that this
maybe now will bring it back to this
paper but
science is kind of the representational
paradigm and i think dean's question is
getting at
what is before what's the before and the
after or the subconscious or the
submerged of science
and then when we're talking about that
representational piece and when we're
talking about science
we're talk we typically talk in terms of
isms
what is where is
how is when we when we set up our our
hypothesis
and i think what this paper if we're
bringing it back to the paper i think
what section five of the paper speaks to
especially when we're talking about the
the functional dimension
is the if
the counter factual
and how they talk in there about how i'm
not sure if it was clark or hoey or one
of them talks about the fact that so a
bacteria doesn't typically
ask the question what if
when it's sampling its environment
so that's that's pre
science
yeah i think that relates a lot to
martin boots's uh guest stream i think
12 on the event-based cognition
and how if there is an event-based
structure to cognitive events
then for any given parameter in that
model
it can be otherwise
you could say like the ball is rolling
off a table
the ball is not rolling off a table
the cup is rolling off the table like
you can start to just do single
mutations
especially the important counterfactuals
for linguistic structures
and then
that might be
closer to what we've seen discussed in
other sims papers as the adaptive active
inference agent going back to earlier
papers citing that but just
that was our previous discussion with
sims this paper has sims like the
pendulum
does not have a counter factual about
whether it could
go on a different axis
it's mechanically constrained whereas
cognitive structures can
engage in counter factual play
in a way that
the pinball machine can't even if the
pinball machine has chaotic
or other types of seemingly agentic
behavior
and then and in that in that
in that space i can be at the top of the
of the ski hill
prior to it prior to a gradient descent
and i can be adaptive meaning i can
close my eyes and do a visualization and
i can also be
variational meaning that i can try to
recreate through my proprioceptive
sensors a sensation of floating
pre pushing off
and engaging with that process right
so again
i the when the when of this i think is
something that really matters i think we
gloss over it or we don't even pay any
attention to it typically because
we want to get to
in the paper it's figure two we wanna
get to figure two
but i think
before there was a figure two
before that there was a plan or a
representation
um
we might wanna ask when plan
if i'm engaging in counter factual
inference prior then doesn't everything
in the diagram
depend on prospecting
up the nodes in that representation
all right do not do i not have to
provision up a format that will be
potentially
something that others can comprehend
as now organized and don't i have to
propose alternative paths as links like
all of those things are pre-planned all
of those things have to be present
pre-science
so we can we can say
well i'm not paying attention to that
now because you know i'm busy putting
processing something that i can now
transfer to other readers and viewers of
this diagram
but i think to ignore those things is to
ignore the difference between a 10 year
old
doing a science experiment and a 40 year
old doing a science experiment
let me give one
thought on that it actually speaks to
this question of whether science is the
same for everybody or different for
everybody
is this the board
exactly as laid out that everybody has
to play by
that's like the game of life
um the board game not the cellular
automata simulator but the board game
there's one path or there's limited
points of agency and then everybody on
the board on that layer one is moving
through life
on the same or on a constrained set of
trajectories so it's like are these the
immutable railroads of decision making
and thought
or
might other people have
different connections or different
decisions
or
totally different railroad stops
or different dimensionality or just
represented in a different format
is it like well here are the battle
lines
that are always going to be the case for
philosophy
and there's going to be some people
whose situation and neurodiversity leads
them to be on this side or this quadrant
or emphasize this component the regime
of attention
or is even that layer
shifting
because there isn't any stability to be
found in
counterfactuals
there you go
back to the questions
it was a great early point about the
rates of change being different because
also that does at least talking about
rates of change kind of evoke numbers
gets the scientists excited because
could there be like a number could it be
a sentiment score
or could it be like this sentence is
totally consistent with both or it's
inconsistent with this could we annotate
the literature and measure
or do surveys or
um actually measure those rates of
change in individuals on their learning
trajectory or in fields
like how could it go from just being a
really insightful
philosophy paper
with a lot of
scholarship
into being something where we can
use some numbers or something
so i see the first three columns
organization structure and
[Music]
content as
the more stable
i think you had another you had another
diagram where you were showing that
going out over longer periods of time
right
so which one do you think is the most
rapidly changing
functional
okay so let's kind of recap them
so organizational seems to be related to
the encapsulation
uh the the organization like the
architectural
features of the world such that the
representation is separated from the
what is represented so like you could
have representation of the sun but then
that's very far
physically from the sun the structural
aspect is related to representational
vehicles to toot that are structurally
similar to the state of affairs in the
world they stand for
so that is the abstract structure of the
representation
having some
congruence or isomorphism or like
similarly some similarity
to
what
um
is being represented
this one
is super dependent on the definition of
representation because someone go well
you can't represent a car in your head
because your head's not a car
content related
having internal models that either
encode environmental contingencies or
sensory motor contingencies
specification
or description of how the world is taken
to be turned
analyzed in terms of correctness or
truth
so that seems to be more consistent with
the car content you know it's like the
youtube content the car content can be
represented if it's stands for something
the content of that message was an
invitation to the birthday party so that
is related to the information or like
the mimetics
especially in a actionable
way
um and then the functional role this is
where we're going to highlight and
hopefully dina i want to hear a little
more about why this one is different
supports vicari's use
before or in the absence of external
events of internal variables of a model
that was discussed in the paper a lot in
the context of sensory motor detachment
and there have been some blurry lines
found there for sure like motor replay
and pre-play so we know that it is on
the spectrum of existing that neural
dynamics but cognitive dynamics involved
during
our involved echoes or anticipations of
them are involved
in the before
and after as well as counterfactuals
before and after
so what is happening with functional
representations and then maybe how does
it relate to active and fep
yeah so i don't i i don't know i know
enough about dreams
and subconsciousness just to get me into
trouble but the first three
when we reorganize through our dreaming
and whatever those representations are
non-representations depending on your
your
wish
those are all backwards looking
typically
and then the functional
that's what segregates it out it's
forward and backwards
so that's to me a huge differentiator
right there
in terms of how much how much or how
long we expect something to stabilize
versus how much we want to act on
something and and generate that change
or outcome that we're seeking
that's why that's why i get back to that
search field
being different than a framework
okay it's a lot to think about but it's
interesting
the organizational
um maybe there's some
dissenting view from this but this is
related to
how the system is arranged
so this one
is
can be thought to be slowly changing
because we're talking about things
which means we're talking something that
has persistence and so the
organizational aspects of systems tend
to be the slowest changing perhaps like
the organization of the servers changes
on a very slow time scale relative to
the processor
then
the structural aspect
also it's very important that it has
persistent like storing a variable in
memory like you want things to stand for
each other for a long time you want the
doi to be a representation of that paper
for a long time
those are also related to like
it's sort of the functional side of
organization like form and function a
little bit but i know for functional is
used later so not to confuse the term
function but this is related to some of
the performative aspects
of
organization and infrastructure and
architecture
so that's also like that's you don't
want the screwdriver to be a different
thing
in your hands that's too slow but maybe
be cool if you can modify or tweak the
tool or like you know unscrew it and
bolt something in a little slower to
make it different but usually you don't
want to change too fast then
but what about the content related this
seems to be also changing
somewhat faster because
environmental
or sensory motor contingencies
that seems like that could change on the
fly
and then i agree that the functional
role as defined here like vicarious
detachment including counter factual
and self-modeling counterfactuals
this is like some of the most
uh rapidly mutating but what do you
think about content also changing fast
well i think whenever i make a mistake
and i accidentally hit the delete button
on my notes how upset i get because the
stability of the content is lost
so i actually see it is still relatively
stable as opposed to something that's
changing rapidly
so
these four
uh
columns here
there is a different temporal aspect
which relates to what you asked earlier
about when
representation so
instead of the possessive do organisms
have representations
or the identitarian
are organisms representations
or the definitional what are
representations
this is the temporal or the dynamical
when our representations well that's not
complete you have to say what it is you
can't just say when it is
well couldn't you just flip the words
wouldn't it be just the other person's
perspective
you can't talk about is without when
so why is that one okay why are there
papers about what is a representation
what is it like to be a bat rather than
when is it
like i don't think it has to be or
i think it's both
the other thing that i would i think we
need to maybe think about a bit is
the first three
um
tend to be on a continuum
that's orthogonal to the fourth
i can organize i can structure and i can
content build
functional now
is orthogonal that i will
because it's going
it's used before
so again back to that temporal aspect
it's both
i i wouldn't drop any of the four
columns i'm just saying that i think
that the fourth column is maybe on a
y-axis relative to the first three that
are on on the x plane
okay a few notes here so before or
in the absence of
right now
isn't it the case that usually
anticipation entails something being
both before and in the absence of i
wonder what it will be like when my
friend comes over that's in the absence
of the event
and it's a counterfactual before but it
may happen it's a prediction it's an
expectation and maybe even an act of
inference it's a preference
so i agree like even the way that the
authors have written it these are
related to architectural and
performative
features of
um
like basically functional or structural
definitions of representations
what they are what they do and then this
is even uses temporal words
as well as counter factual words though
um and those are probably like used
elsewhere in the paper but that's a very
interesting
uh distinction and so it's like there's
our map but you know how easy is it to
just lay out the map and go all right
here's northern california here's a map
instead of um the temporal aspect
and i think that also shines a light
actually on another feature of what
people would call science which is like
science the metric system
and then like okay you've gone too far
with the metric time but then pretty
much on a lot of the other fronts except
in the united states um the metric
system
has
um holds
as how people are sense making in terms
of like distance and time and other
units and that's kronos like
like like um chronology and time in the
decimal time
and then kairos is like the timeliness
and there's other ways to think about
time so we kind of open it up and it
just um
makes me wonder okay what else is handed
with the map
is there a time object how do we share
time
along with the map is that attention is
um
focus times time times
all these other things so how do we
convey the temporal aspect
and instead of just this gene regulatory
network or this is that the map here
or the map and the math and the
territory how do we bring the temporal
along
so
i wonder like
about the temporal also and especially
like now that we're kind of delving into
um like quantum aspects
because you know like the the
simultaneous existence of more than one
state right is possible and so is the
the
is it possible to be like building and
like executing your model at the same
time like can
is it input then output is it always
sequential or or is there some
kind of like
simultaneous
happening right like that's that's going
on there i don't know
oh blue that's perfect for the next
question i wanted to ask so is one of
the assumptions here
that there's a a continuum
like
if then between i can and i will because
this was a debate that i got into with
people forever when i was in education
that there's some sort of an assumption
that because i can therefore i will
well i wouldn't jump off a cliff even
with a parachute on there's no will for
me to do that because that's just not my
it's not my jam
but but if
speaking
if if if organization is on the on the x
and structural is on the x and content
is on the x but functional is on the y
now i can separate the two things out
and and as you said if i go back to the
quantum level
now i'm i'm pre
decision branch in that diagram
you notice that the diagram is basically
unidirectional it's always heading to a
particular outcome it's always
i can make this decision branch moment
therefore i will arrive at
representational or non-representational
and i'm
with you i'm not so sure that
previous to this that it isn't
bi-directional it isn't functional it
isn't orthogonal i think it could be all
three of those things
blue would you like to say anything or
can i
all right
two points i would be remiss not to make
first the tetrahedron and fuller
synergetics gives us a mnemonic to have
four spatial dimensions so
this
four column scheme all of them can be
four intersecting spatial dimensions
they're coordinated at 60 degrees not 90
degrees and then the second
point is like this um one directional
maze reminded me a lot of the way that
people study decision making and path
finding or figuring whichever one may be
in ants which is there's some laboratory
maze like a y maze or a t maze or maybe
some branch on a tree in nature
and then
for the purposes of the science so
called the paper
it's going to be like we counted them as
going down a certain branch making a
decision at the node when they went five
centimeters past the branch point and
didn't return so it's like this is the
the line that you trip when it goes from
zero to one on that number and that's
what gets fed into the scientific uh
process and the method the observations
of the literature and the statistics and
all of that but then if you're watching
the ant or if you look at the video
maybe they dwell at the node or they
turn around
or they walk down one and then they come
back or like even they go far down one
and they come back so it is very
interesting and it's a subtle graphical
point but one that would be almost seen
as like what do you mean how could these
be undirected edges
well what if we say hey let's start at
representational fep it's it's just
where we're going to start today and
then
let's pull back to the vicarious use of
variables
now where can we go from there to
sensory motor detachment or we can take
no and all of a sudden we're a
non-representational fep because
they're only one step away
because they're both outcomes of the
decision about the vicarious use of
variables
so
i hope those are some interesting points
and i think that relates a lot to the
discussions that we've been having in
edu about cyclic curriculum
and you touched on it we i'm going to
just bring it i'm going to reduce it not
over reduce it i'm going to reduce it to
to your point daniel there can be a yes
there can be a no and there could be a
maybe
and the maybe part is what's being left
out of this
cool i'll read a comment from serval in
the chat
uh who i was also thinking of when we
talked about like science as a human
phenomena and all of that i think
survival has a lot to say on that
cerval wrote
considering many world
hey dean i'm going to read sorel's
comment considering many world type
theories
is it possible that can entails will it
would be a distributional property
though not a trajectory property
okay i have to think of that in terms of
what i how i set up entailment
um
[Music]
maybe
i'm not trying to i'm not trying to duck
i think there will be times when my
confidence
through my ability to say that i've done
something before
leads me to a lower threshold around
will
but then sometimes it doesn't
so i'm not i'm not trying to be evasive
but i can think of times when it can
entail and i can also think of times
when it very much does not
so will
it's a short english word
it's could refer to something that will
happen
like the ball will go to the bottom of
the bowl
unless anything else stops it from doing
that
or it can refer to sort of that
motivational psychological energy which
is related to agency
and so it's real it's kind of an
interesting
uh
congealed word because agency
and will are very related
and uh i'm just trying to think if
they're positively related like to feel
that you have the choice is to have the
agency
and that can be seen as willpower
whereas willpower doesn't come into play
in situations where there's no agency if
you just need to sit in the seat on the
airplane
it doesn't require any
willpower or agency
for that action to occur
so i'm just thinking about cervel's
comment and um the distributional
property like counter factuals
do we engage with them as a possible
uh
cosmological reality like in the many
world type theories or just
uh cognitive
possibilities
so they can be engaged with without
taking on like a cosmological
meaning
and then what does that mean about our n
equals one trajectory
the specifics of our
kind of
entity in motion
and then the the distribution of
perhaps different types of
counterfactuals
or different kinds of
possible stochastic rollouts of the
system given really similar starting
conditions
and that's where the wheel can entail
the can i can start out by asking what
if
but i still have to select
the can the which if
so that's what again i
at some point we can have we can see a
relationship of entailment but i think
as
as a as a quantum question
they're orthogonal can and will are not
one leads necessarily to the other
so
just to kind of like play on words and
loop back around to what i was
talking about earlier um like can is an
affordance right like so if you have an
affordance like like that doesn't mean
that that you'll use it right and will
like means i i will choose or or implies
that you have some agency right i
choose to um you know
not start a fight with a flight
attendant while i'm sitting in my seat
on the airplane or whatever because you
can do all kinds of things any any you
get many affordances
um
and i just wonder how this ties into
these representational and
non-representational
aspects of of the fep like really when i
was talking about free will earlier if
internal states are a direct
representation of external states
it seems to me like i kind of feel like
there's
less
options there
whereas internal and external states
have coupled dynamics
that kind of leaves some
like
mystical
fluff outside like that i can
potentially leverage with my own choice
or
something like that i mean i don't know
what to call it mystical fluff but but
um it leaves something unsaid right like
there's a coupling it's like a hidden
there's a hidden states there that like
are only that that's where i can impose
my will
well i'm gonna put that fluff on a
pedestal
i'm gonna honor the fluff because i do
think that there are actual
times when
the
the ability not to be captured by our
observations is actually
an advantage so mystical meh
may be uncertain
yes and and is and there are there's
other advantages to that at times
yes
so we call it fluff but i think
sometimes
um we don't pay it enough respect
i think that
relates to the cloud of unknowing
which is perhaps a text if somebody
wants to go into a more esoteric avenue
but i'd like to return to the figure
and ask what either of you
thought about figure one how does that
play
into this conversation we've been having
like
what does this entity and action
partitioning
have to do with science is this
unique to active inference are other
partitionings possible
does it
could it be another way
i think this is a pretty stable
representation
and it and i think it and i think it
does honor to the
the um
scale-free aspects of what the free
energy principle is pointing to in terms
of a
in terms of as a statistical
pathway
yeah i mean how many
debates and uncertainties could be
prevented by saying this is a
representation of an entity
and having people know what was meant by
representation
right because it's like i made this
representation of an entity
i think it does this useful thing
those points cannot be
false
they're assertions by a person
and what would be disagreed with
that it's not a representation someone
could say there's a more useful
representation or more good true
beautiful
simple
but then let's see it
and then we can use science to compare
representations because that would be
okay
right
and then you said it does honor to the
scale free
so
the only thing that kind of hints
otherwise is the person and the world
kind of gives a scale
uh indicator
for this model
but without that iconography
it would
uh be
and also adding in perhaps a legend or
description
of what the edges mean
because it does say schematic of
reciprocal exchanges
and it uses statistical vocabulary
but it also uses actual like ontological
vocabulary in the terms of actuators
so are these the physical things that
are doing the actuating
or are they the statistical
or informational exchanges or is this
the representation the form of the
scientists model so we're only ever
talking about scientists using these
models so we're only ever talking about
that kind of nexus where we're referring
to both loosely
and so it shouldn't be interpreted as
either of them specifically
it's just dialogue
there's a lot of ways to interpret what
the edges are and
they might have similar different
labelings and different
schemes
but it is statistical
it is quantifiable
it's amenable
it's a qualitative topological
partitioning that's amenable
and beyond to certain quantitative
analyses like if you can draw it like
that
you might be able to do a bayesian graph
and then there's software toolkits and
there's implementable algorithms and
then there might be some quite
interesting
guarantees or tendencies
with certain architectures for example
to perform predictive processing or to
have learning anticipation and memory or
to engage in control or anticipatory
control
but that's definitely some of the most
core
iconography that we've seen i mean 50 of
papers or what we'll find out blue
have the action loop
because
what little side hustle have you blue
got going here
we're trying we're trying to um
read more papers together
and learn about them
okay
but it's interesting how often this has
come up and
sometimes authors draw on the same image
other times they do different and
sometimes the arrows are just the clock
like just a uni-directional flow other
times there are some bi-directional
arrows
and
um
the
there are several guest streams on the
more technical aspects there but um
let's return to the general questions
anyways anything else to say on figure
one though like just on this
like what is this
how does it think this represents better
the
eye fixating on the
on the pop fly
than it does on the physics model and so
i think it's until something as you said
until somebody comes along with a better
representation one that
that seems to give us the maximum amount
of information that we need
versus the
maximum that we can handle i think this
is a this is a good rep
great and very satisfying conclusion
it's
yeah
sorry uh i i really think that they're
um what's not shown in this
representation and what i feel like is
always left out
is the fact that
that the
there are some states are hidden right
and so like where is the hiding here
what is hidden from what um in this and
so like the sensory states we don't even
know
if like we perceive i mean we know that
we all perceive temperature differently
like some people i'm cold in this room
but many people would be comfortable and
some people like my favorite color is
purple my daughter's favorite color is
yellow so
like we don't perceive things in the
same way
and so there's there's always something
hidden from
everyone else and i think that this this
schematic kind of leaves that out i've
seen the hidden states um represented
well in other like action perception
loops but i i think that it's important
to um
recognize like what's obvious and what's
not
if i could give a
one thought there then dean so i think
there's there's two levels of like what
are the hidden states
from the perspective of the internal
states the system of interest the
external states are hidden states
implicitly are explicitly modeled but
they're the ones that are never directly
observable
they're only
observed through their proxy sensory
states and enacted or the transition
frequencies are modified through policy
selection through action so within the
model within the tetrahedra
the hidden states are relative to the
internal states on the other side of the
markov blanket and then there's like the
implicit tetrahedra which is like us
modeling this four-fold partitioning
and then everything that's not included
as a variable in that statistical model
is like implicitly a hidden state
but then what is that
but then we'd have a different model if
it wasn't a hidden estate
and the other thing i think is that the
vertical line
between sensory states and action states
if you tip that 90 degrees it would look
like a blank
even though it has two points on the end
of it and i think that's that blank is
by definition hidden state it's to be
filled in
so i think i think again
you can you can fill in the blank or you
can leave it blank and say because it's
blank
that is by definition hidden
so another
related point thanks for bringing that
up dean
is um
there's there's one edge that's not
shown here but has featured very
importantly in recent discussions on
active and that's the sigma
or the mapping function from number 26
and number 32
a mapping function
of internal states to external states
now
look at axle constant and yellow
brundenberg's work to think about how
the niche is also doing like
anticipatory modeling of the individual
so the other way but let's just focus on
the entity and its mapping to external
states it's predicting external states
or at least acting as if or can be
modeled as if so there is an edge there
that we've seen in
modern work
it's not drawn here which actually might
suggest either the inheritance of a
legacy graphical pattern or
some
preferences or conclusions about what
these edges do represent again even
though they're unlabeled so that's one
edge that we've been hearing more about
and then i think another edge that dean
just highlighted is this one directly
between sensory and action states
and again the clock flow doesn't have
this
the one that's just internal action
external sense that doesn't have the
sense action bridge
right and
it depends a lot on what these things
mean
but
it'd be cool to
understand what is meant by the
backwards connections
as well as by the vertical connections
and why are there not backwards
connections
between action and internal and sensory
and external it's like
it's really a four by four
matrix with some connections and that's
how we've seen it represented as the
sparse connectivity matrix
in
number 32
and thinking about the um way that we
model complex systems and generate
approximations that sometimes can also
retain some other features like the
highly optimistic exponent so
some thoughts there blue
so we've definitely seen um internal
states and sensory states like that
reciprocality happen
um but i do i always wonder why like
especially since we did the mental
action paper like how
action states don't influence internal
states and so for me like when you take
action like when you
practice playing the piano
that affects your internal states
totally like not just through external
states or even mental action like where
you're doing nothing with external
states it's entirely internal um and so
i always wonder why that action and
internal um
is there but i i less so wonder why
there's not a reciprocal loop between
external states and sensory states like
what like i never want the sensory
states to go back to the external states
um
for me that doesn't make sense and maybe
you guys have an example where it does
make sense but i always want the action
and internal states to loop together to
have it bi-directional
here's one possibility on the sense back
to external but it depends of course on
a specific interpretation of those
a photon
let's just assume it's out there
it hits the retina
if we talk about the retina as a sense
state using it very loosely not the
statistical variable correlating to the
sense state but the actual retina it's
the
absorption of the photon
that changes the niche
to be sensed like if you're going to be
sensing molecules from the ants cuticle
you have to take some
you could sense from the ground the ones
that have already been deposited but if
you want some from the thing
you have to take a sample
and so that may and whether that would
be better understood as being an action
in the niche is another question but
like
you do have to change the external state
to be half skin in the game
no and i just thought of it as you're
saying that like the observer phenomenon
right like so there's that too right
just just the act of sensing it changes
it or is the observer phenomena does
that come from sense
does that come from
internal states does it come from action
states are the observers just acting in
a way that
might fit in within an action state but
those are really interesting questions
dean
no i just think you're right i think
both of you
are
we're getting we're getting closer i
don't think we'll ever fly directly into
the sun but we're getting warmer
yeah this uh we'll have another few
minutes to talk this has been a really
great discussion and i look forward to
like re-listening to it and discussing
more then of course feel so appreciative
that we'll have a dot too as well
so
we
can return to some of our early ones
free will
maybe save it for the dot 2 or
if we want to talk about it now
i think we've blurred and fuzzed some of
these lines a little bit so we did kind
of get there let's see what else we had
down and of course if anyone in the last
30 minutes has any
questions they want to
write so steven wrote i like your method
to work backwards in the flow diagram
start at
representative or non-representative
assumptions or perhaps conclusions like
starting at those endpoints as
assumptions then looking for prediction
errors in our action perception this
maintains uncertainty in ways that does
not happen when following the causal
effective correlations
that's sort of like 20 questions it's
framed as a game of
um
oh i'm sorry i didn't know that
mentioning common children's games was
funny um
that's framed as a game of going from
the most uncertain towards more
certainty like if you were asking
uninformative questions
what are you doing if you're not if
you're just getting like and that's
information theory kind of exemplified
you're reducing the set
of what you can be
um
guessing with the preference to like win
within 20 questions
and then this is
as steven is pointing out kind of the
other direction
but then what does that look like and
that is almost inflating uncertainty at
least in the information theory sense
so here's steven's question and then
either of you if you have a thought on
this
do we model the temporal lags in
dynamical change between sensory state
in relation to changes in action state
so maybe a related question would be how
do time scales and temporal lags
play into
our
modeling of action perception and
cognition
this is why i kept saying to young
people when in doubt
zoom in zoom out and it wasn't just zoom
in zoom out in a sort of a
in a visual sense you have to zoom in
and zoom out on the temporal sets
as well you have to think about the
you have to think about the unit of
analysis both as a as a
as an object but also
the
as a time of the length of time
something can remain stable or not
i don't think we i don't think we're
naturally inclined to include
the time frame
as much as we're inclined to include the
did it change
did it float
did it burn whatever whatever it is that
we're waiting to see what happens next
we don't tend to give as much attention
over to how long did it take
i'll give a complimentary thought which
is
more related to the kinds of models that
we've specifically seen in actinf so the
deep temporal models or sophisticated
active inference
in for example a three time step model
at time step one it's doing inference on
one two and three that's
planning as inference in anticipation at
time step three it can still be
calculating the model in light of
incoming evidence about time step one
two and three
which is related to memory and learning
and all these other sorts of so-called
backwards looking types of inference so
there's like anticipation there's now
casting and then there's reconstruction
of your recent and long-term past and
how that's related to
identity so i think the the question
um do we or how do we model
the temporal or just the temporality of
sense and action states the answer
from model based science is
what's the time horizon parameter on the
model that we ran
oh it was 15 days
okay well then we modeled the temporal
lag
up to 15 days
and that is what we modeled
and
that is sort of where the uh
scale free becomes the scale friendly
becomes the scale specific
and then that's the
the most that it contracts down to is
that one specific model as deployed by
those researchers
here's another question from stephen
when do we sense and when do we act
when do our sense states update when
does our generative model update and
when do our action states update
i'll start with the model based science
one which is again it would just be the
specifics of how the pseudocode and the
actual computer code were written which
line of code updates first that's the
narrow answer but what about a more
broader answer
does it depend on how open we are
how how how
how
confident competent we are in
staying in an uncertain non-specific
space and can we can we necessarily know
going in
how long that will be
i don't i don't know i don't know how
long
and what about precognition right like
if we you know expand to that
possibility like like i knew that was
gonna happen i mean that happens to all
of us right we all experience that like
oh i knew that was gonna happen like if
i you know step on this ice cube it's
gonna like this ice pile it's gonna
crack through to water or whatever like
i knew that was gonna happen so so we're
able to kind of perceive things before
they happen and so
i don't know like is there not
necessarily the the temporal
um separation this makes me like think
back to like shanna dobson and like the
flattening of the time diamond right
like so so really like um
is that um
is it necessary that there's sequence
here or can it just all be happening
simultaneously that kind of relates to
what i was asking earlier to like at
is there some kind of
simultaneous update sensing action
possibility and i think that there is i
mean i i don't think that
um not in a computational model because
you know code just runs like it is but
um i think
in our model it's possible yeah
okay one more general and then more
specific comment the 4d spatial model
tetrahedral synergetic geometry you have
space and time four dimensions spatially
represented rather than the xyz you have
three spatial dimensions and then
there's like the special question of how
does t come into play so some is known
there and some is not known there but
when and where and how are of course
very linked
and if we take model-based science
seriously then they're also very
enabled and constrained by the kinds of
models we have so maybe it's related to
how we think about geometry
and then
the sense and action
are they continuous or are they discrete
we've seen recently decosta at all like
the synthesis of active inference on
discrete state spaces
and then we've also seen some of uh alex
chance's work on the continuous
control
settings with like the mountain car
which is not just um the uh discrete
case
so it's just interesting to see how
uh
some of the theory goes out in front and
then there's parallel lines of
mathematical development with continuous
and discrete modeling like digital and
analog modeling and sometimes those
types of modeling scientifically are
very well reconciled
and other times they result in pretty
fundamentally different patterns
like there are certain equations where
the discretized form or the version
that's computed without really high
precision numbers on a computer has
really different behavior than the other
kinds of models which
gets at the importance of thinking about
how the model is is
framed and then also applied because
like if the precision of the processor
matters for what the paper discovers
then
shouldn't that be a part of the
consideration
okay
here's a few of the other comments and
for thirty six one two so by the way
we'll write down any other questions so
if anyone in the last few minutes has
some questions
they can ask and we'll be just writing
things down
getting excited for
dot two and if anybody wants to join who
wasn't here today they're also very
welcome too
how is representation related to
autopoesis
so refresher autopoetic system is
capable of producing and maintaining
itself by creating its own parts
so how does representation differ or
does it differ for a system that is just
engineered and secreted into the niche
like a computer
versus potentially something that is
reassembling its parts continually why
does that matter if it does
that is that a
thing to look at and point to daniel
that sounds good yeah yeah not i'm
trying to push it on but i mean
the reality is is that
we can take each of the of the different
segments the organizational the
structural
and the content related and then
put them through the autopoetic grinder
and see what pops out the other side
okay great suggestion apply this to the
four columns
um
what other things would be fun to
discuss in
dot 2 or what else can go through the
four column grinder or what would be any
other question that any of you have
in the in the in the 0.2 also if we can
we can spend a little bit of time on
some of the
some of the comments that were in the
section 5 of the paper
specifically around how
we face state from
potentially they didn't say that this is
true but they said if if this claim is
true we could be face stating from not
representational too representational
maybe maybe could we spend a little bit
of time not just looking at the
autopilosis aspect of that but how does
how does that density form in the in
relationship to this idea of modeling
ourselves
great question
here's a question that um stephen wrote
so feel free to give a thought on it or
we can
uh push it
it was
will robotics or neurophenomenology
help most in testing these complex
temporal dynamics in a realist way
i'm just going to say that's a great
question and i think we need the person
who asked the question to come on and
chat with us about that a little bit
we're just delegating so hard here blue
go ahead
so something that i've brought up i
think in the dodge zero is like i would
really like to tease apart the
similarities and differences between
like structural aspects
and
content related aspects
i'm not entirely certain like that's a
fuzzy blurred
line for me
um there so maybe we could get into that
a little bit more
i agree it's fuzzy for me too
these are awesome questions too thanks
for writing us all out blue well we have
multiple pages so we have
auto polices
from non-rep to non-rep to rep and back
and forth or
whatever else how does that form in the
context of self-representation
i think there's a few hamlet quotes that
will come into play there
then stephen's question about technology
and realism
structural content aspects
detached representations in the
neurobehavioral systems in the sensory
motor loop
niche modification
stigma g and the digital case extended
cognitive systems that include digital
and uh mirror adaptive systems
steven's singing 80 songs in the chat i
believe
thinking through other minds and
multi-scale integration one of sims
other papers
how are they related
does the fep exist independently or only
in the mirror
a lot of ways to answer that one
[Music]
one part
we could look into now or
maybe in the dot two would be the free
expected free energy and variational
free energy
and how they play different roles in the
fep
these are also some things like if
people are watching live or in the next
few days then
they can write a comment on it or um get
in touch with us or like if they want to
submit a question or
they can come on and discuss it in the
dot too
variational
and expected
free energy
there's a lot of parts to the paper
oh and action-oriented representation we
didn't
get to that slide in the dot zero
but just what is what is action oriented
representation we've talked about
representations today but then did we
talk about
were we implicitly talking about
action-oriented representations are
those a subclass how are they different
any other yeah
in our in our like system in like human
cognition there are some
um
like hard-coded representations that we
have um
like action-oriented maybe one of them
um like kinesthetic memory and also like
visual recognition systems and
it's really interesting that um
and perhaps easy to apply
the fep to
specific cognitive systems
like subsystems
but
it's
really much more difficult when we have
like multiple competing processes like
we're not just
playing the piano and we're not just
looking at the piano keys like we're
doing both of those things at the same
time and lots of other things like we
might be you know having some memory of
one time that we heard the song that
we're playing or something like that so
it's really interesting to think about
um
representation and all the ways that it
exists also even in memory right like
the memory representation is um
is it's like a
it's not that's not a hard-coded um
thing it's really squishy and it's it's
um subject to change through time and
you know we might remember a situation
like you can tell me your phone number
right now and i'll remember it you know
in five minutes but in five days no like
or something like that so um i don't
know it's really interesting
to think about the fep and how it can
apply in this overarching way
um where there are multiple competing
goals and
priorities and
um yeah
that
one thought i hope i'm not
misrepresenting an empirical result was
in fruit fly the drosophila
they
found that uh short-term memories
didn't require protein synthesis like
just second to second some sound or some
symbol could be associated with a
preferred or repulsive outcome
but
preventing protein synthesis block the
consolidation of memory and perhaps
that's similar to other systems and so
there's kind of like
the resonant neural structures
that are just using
the system's connections as they are
that's sort of one perhaps faster mode
of cognition that's like running around
figure two
and then there's a
restructuring
that requires changing the model like
structure learning but that also
connects to realism because we're
talking about the
synapses and the neurogenesis like of
specific
cells that could be maybe measured and
then the neurophysiology and the
behavior can be
observed as well
if we have integrative frameworks like
active
so
like
it also relates to dean's comment about
the scales the time scales of change
like neural circuits cannot be changing
at a time scale faster than neural
firing so how does the spiking component
or the other sensory transduction or
other chemical components how do those
overlapping time scales
coordinate
this reminds me to daniel of something
that we talked about like the very first
time we met um because it was a recent
experiment at that time about the memory
transfer between snails um via injection
of of rna
um so that was like an interesting
possible
memory storage um
and i'm not sure what what else has you
know developed from that but but also
we've talked about
you know ants and what
um how they leave like
they like told me like that they're just
throwing up rna like they're throwing up
all the time all over the place and like
maybe leaving chemical like rna traces
for each other um we talked about that
too so maybe i don't know if you want to
expand on that or or does that tie into
this protein synthesis um you know
thing
one thought on that it was a recent uh
ant paper where basically the act of
mating which we won't describe on this
family-friendly discussion
directly infuses neurotransmitters into
the recipient and that changes their
behavior and induces all these other
hormonal changes and so the realism of
cognition like the embodiment and the
physicality of these systems
it is perturbable by infusions of
neurotransmitters
in
other neural systems and in us so that's
sort of where realism can't be
eradicated
amidst all of these representations
because
things do hit our head and molecules do
diffuse it's kind of like grounding it
and that's i think why it's such an
interesting and um
integrative area with a lot of
contention
because the four e side
is holding down that
real side
and then the science side so called is
holding down the abstractions and the
representations
and then cognitive science especially as
applied to humans
is kind of where it meets in the middle
it's like well yeah you're talking about
embedded cognition and active cognition
but that's your cognition
that's modeling
and so then you get
um all kinds of fun
viewpoints and
ideas because
of
how mixed and complex that
area is
thanks blue and dean
and those who participated in chat for
this really great
discussion i hope you can
digest it and learn in the next week and
reflect on some of these questions and
that anyone can ask more questions or
start to prepare some thoughts so that
they can also be involved because this
was really fun
all right
we've got one question yes statement
um
every one of these live streams i don't
know
ultimately how it's decided which order
that we do them in but the fact that
we've gone
from conner's paper to magee's paper to
this one
whether it was done with some sort of
intent
and looking back a lot back to the
future
or it was just okay well i think we'll
we'll do this one next and see what
happens i think the order of these last
three papers in particular
has been
[Music]
pretty just the order in which we've
looked at them has generated a whole
bunch of
interesting
ideas including sort of the
the idea of tr intransitivity in the
last paper now potentially
influencing how we've discussed this
paper so
again i don't know how much pre-thought
goes into that but if there was some
pre-thought that went into putting these
papers in this particular order
it's been very uh helpful
and one other thing if
if i find something happy
because it's true i'm gonna laugh
and if i find something happy because
it's playing a game like 20 questions or
any game
i'm gonna laugh so
if i can't be
uh if i can't enjoy and uh
and really appreciate
the sophistication of the conversation
here i probably wouldn't show up so
thanks to both of you
you can make me read active papers but
you can't make me have fun
but just to give it one closing answer
information for anybody who wants to
like get involved with the discussions
here's our coda for the dot coms unit
and so here's the live stream table the
one that gets represented on the
viewable public one so we have all the
papers planned like in this case up till
37 38 39 40 up through the end of march
so we try to plan the papers in advance
so that people can have time to read
them and commit to collaborating on the
dot zero background video and then we
have papers to potentially discuss
and so here people add papers and then
they click a heart and dean we just
sorted by hearts
and then we picked the papers
that were on the four top papers
and we said okay we're going to read
these four
for um 36 seven eight nine
um
yeah those
and then we emailed the authors
and so we of different papers and we
said well what dates might work because
we always will prefer to schedule a
paper that we want to read when the
authors want to join and so that's kind
of our first um like the way that we
pull
papers out like we set the dates for um
the quantum free energy discussions in
march and then we work backwards from
there and then just try to not
do two
um
[Music]
not even overlapping papers just try to
provide
rhythm and novelty and
philosophy and
technical details so it's sort of a
local decision making
based upon
the votes that people provide who are
participating in the dot coms unit
and pretty random yeah and just what
people surface
that's going to say that's a pretty
serendipitous uh order then that's
fantastic it's fun um and and if anybody
watching or listening wants to suggest a
paper for the live stream uh please do
so yeah
all right thank you dean and blue so see
you all next week for the dot 2. bye
you